Traitorous thing
감히 가문을 배신하려고 해?
Look at our ancestors
조상님들 앞에서
Think of what you've done
네가 저지른 일을 돌이켜 봐라
Do you still know your family name?
네 성씨를 기억이나 하느냐?
Chen
진 씨입니다
Do you still know?
기억은 하고 있구나?
Don't think those old ones
그 늙은이들이
Can protect you forever
평생 널 지켜줄 거라 생각하지 마라
Let her kneel here
그냥 여기 무릎 꿇려 두어라
For two days to clear her head
이틀 동안 이러고 있으면 정신 차리겠지
No one is to give her food or water
먹을 것도 가져다주지 마라
The Great Xuan Dynasty with centuries of foundation
수백 년의 기틀을 가진 대선(大宣) 왕조는
Seems to have long grown accustomed to a corner of the realm
이미 한쪽 구석에 안주하는 데 익숙해진 듯합니다
As long as there's the Tianhe as a barrier
천하(天河)의 험준함만 있으면
The world can safely remain in the south
사람들은 안심하고 남방에 머물며
Amidst song and dance
평화로운 삶을 누릴 수 있습니다
They've long forgotten the Wutu's iron hooves marching south
그들은 이미 오노의 남하하는 철기병을 잊었고
Forgotten the shame of being forced to move the capital
강제로 천도해야 했던 치욕을 잊었으며
Forgotten the fate of the northern people
북방 옛 백성들의 생사조차 잊었습니다
Whether called virtuous ministers
소위 현명한 재상과 충신이라 해도
Or treacherous ministers
간신이나 아첨꾼이라 해도
In the end, they're all just servants of one family
결국 한 가문, 한 성씨를 위한 신하에 불과합니다
Just as the Grand Historian once said
태사공 사마천이 옛날에 말했듯이
All under heaven come bustling for profit
"세상 사람들은 모두 이익을 위해 모이고"
All under heaven go rushing for profit
"세상 사람들은 모두 이익을 위해 흩어진다"
If one can protect one family's interests
만약 한 집안의 이익을 지키고
If one can make one clan prosper
한 가문을 흥하게 할 수 있다면
What does it matter what name this realm bears
이 나라와 왕조가 누구의 것인지
Or to whom this land belongs?
내 발 아래 땅이 누구의 소유인지
What does it matter?
그것이 과연 무슨 의미가 있겠습니까?
In these turbulent times
풍전등화 같은 시기에
Some are full of concern, thinking of danger in peace
어떤 이는 평화 속에서도 위기를 염려하고
Some are wise and self-preserving, thinking of retreat
어떤 이는 자기 보호를 최우선으로 삼으며
Some clearly see the times and quietly think of change
또 어떤 이는 정세를 분별해 은밀히 변화를 계획합니다
After all, is it for one family's benefit in one generation
과연 이것은 한 집안, 한 성씨의 일시적인 이익을 위한 것인가?
Or for the welfare of all under heaven for a hundred years...
아니면 온 천하 백성들을 위해 백년대계를 위한 것인가?
I hope you
이 시대의 거센 물결 속에서 영원히 간직하기를 바랍니다
Your original heart...
자신의 초심을...